Guide to the Weston La Barre Papers, 1930-1996 UA.29.02.0070
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Weston La Barre papers
1930-1996
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
La Barre, Weston, 1911-
UA.29.02.0070
31 Linear Feet
Weston La Barre (1911-1996) was an anthropology professor at Duke University from 1946 to 1977. Prior to coming to Duke, La Barre worked in military intelligence in the U.S. Navy during World War II. The Weston La Barre Papers include correspondence, publications, lectures, committee materials, teaching materials, photographs, audio recordings, scrapbooks and other materials. La Barre's professional interests included cultural anthropology, religion, psychodelic drugs such as peyote, and psychology. Major correspondents include George Devereux, Allen Ginsberg, Alexander Morin, Richard Evans Schultes, and Howard Stein. English.
30,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Materials such as private legal and financial records, counseling records, student and faculty records and information, classified information, job candidate information, letters of recommendation, employment records, certain congressional papers, and medical records may all be protected by law or by third party privacy rights. Living individuals have a legally enforceable right to privacy, and release of personally identifiable information contained in archival collections may give rise to liability (e.g., for defamation of character or invasion of privacy).
Audio recordings require a listening copy; contact University Archives for more information.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Weston La Barre Papers was received by the University Archives as a gift in 1981, 1987, 1989, 1990, 1992, 1993, 1996, and 1997.
Biographical Note
Weston La Barre was born on December 13, 1911, in Uniontown, Pennsylvania. Until about the age of 30, La Barre sometimes went by the names "I. Weston LaBarrer" and "Raoul La Barre" before using "Weston La Barre" exclusively. La Barre attended Princeton University and graduated with an A.B. degree in 1933. He then attended Yale University and received his Ph.D. degree in 1937. La Barre conducted a number of anthropological field trips beginning in 1935, when he studied Kiowa Indians. He conducted research on peyote in 1936, which grew into his dissertation and later his book, The Peyote Cult. In 1937, La Barre traveled to Bolivia to research the Aymara.
La Barre began teaching in 1939 at Rutgers University, the same year he married Maurine Boie, a social worker. After World War II broke out, the La Barres moved to Utah to work for the War Relocation Authority. After a short period, Weston La Barre joined the Navy and was trained a parachutist. He was assigned to parachute into an area of Laos because of his previous study of Southeast Asian ethnography. However, due to changes caused by the newly created Office of Strategic Services, La Barre spent several months each in Calcutta, Kunming, and Chungking before being moved to Kandy, Ceylon (now Sri Lanka) for nine months. He then returned to the United States and worked with the Atlantic Fleet before commissioned out of the naval reserve in 1946.
In that same year, La Barre was offered a teaching position at Duke University, a position he held until 1977. During his Duke career, La Barre taught many anthropology courses on culture, religion, psychiatry, and symbolism. He was known as a popular, if difficult, professor. He co-currently taught in the University of North Carolina (UNC) at Chapel Hill School of Medicine from 1956 to 1959, and was a visiting clinical professor of psychiatry at UNC from 1959 to 1969. In addition to his teaching duties, La Barre lectured at hundreds of universities and conferences and published numerous articles. He also published several books during his Duke career, including The Aymara Indians of the Lake Titicaca Plateau (1948), The Human Animal (1954), Materia Medica of the Aymara Indians (1959), They Shall Take Up Serpents: Psychology of the Southern Snake-Handling Cult (1966), The Ghost Dance: Origins of Religion (1970). In 1970, he became a James B. Duke Professor of Anthropology.
La Barre retired in 1977, but continued to publish articles and books. Books published after La Barre's retirement include Culture in Context (1980), Muelos: A Stone Age Superstition About Sexuality (1985), Shadow of Childhood: Neotony and the Biology of Religion (1991), and Jonathan (1993, published under the name Jonathan Crocker).
La Barre's wife passed away in 1991. They had three children: John, David, and An. Weston La Barre passed away on March 13, 1996 in Chapel Hill. He was 84 years old.
Collection Overview
The Weston La Barre Papers include correspondence, publications, lectures, committee materials, teaching materials, photographs, audio recordings, scrapbooks and other materials related to the personal life and professional career of anthropologist Weston La Barre. The collection is arranged into 8 series. The first series, Personal, contains materials related to La Barre's family, friends, education, and Navy career during World War II. The next series, Correspondence, contains extensive chronological files of letters to and from La Barre's colleagues and friends. Several correspondents were filed by name, including George Devereux, Allen Ginsberg, Alexander Morin, Richard Evans Schultes, and Howard Stein. The following series, Publications, includes articles and books that La Barre wrote during his long career. It also includes drafts, editing notes, correspondence, and other materials related to the writings. Next, Lectures and Addresses includes the text of many speeches La Barre made across the country, as well as materials related to the conferences and events at which La Barre spoke.
La Barre's participation in conferences, committees, editing projects, and research is documented in the Professional Activities series. The Duke University series contains teaching materials like tests, quizzes, and syllabi. It also contains administrative information from the Department of Anthropology, and a scrapbook and memoir by La Barre recalling the controversy over a possible Nixon Presidential Library at Duke. The next series, Audio Recordings, contains a small selection of speeches and music on anthropological subjects. Finally, the Scrapbooks series contains a number of scrapbooks documenting La Barre's travels in the Navy, on anthropological and research voyages, and for vacation. There are also a large number of scrapbooks in which La Barre appeared to collect clippings of anthropological or psychological interest.
For several of the series (including Correspondence, Publications, Lectures and Addresses, Professional Activities, and Duke University), La Barre annotated the folders with comments about the events, people, and places described within the documents. Because these folders were physically deteriorating, the comments have been photocopied and placed in the front of the corresponding file. La Barre also occasionally annotated individual items, apparently years after the documents were originally created.
Related Material
Papers of Raoul Weston La Barre
National Anthropological Archives, Smithsonian Institution
Anthropology, Cultural; Anthropology; Scrapbooks; World War, 1939-1945 -- Military intelligence -- United States; Psychotropic drugs; Photographs; Psychology and religion; Psychology; Sound recordings; Anthropology -- Research; Anthropology -- Religious aspects; La Barre, Weston, 1911-; La Barre, Weston, 1911-; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Duke University. Dept. of Anthropology; Duke University -- Faculty; Devereux, George, 1908-; United States. Navy; Stein, Howard F.; Schultes, Richard Evans; Morin, Alexander J., 1920-
- Personal, 1930-1988
  Scope and Contents note
  The Personal series contains an assortment of materials related to La Barre's family, education, his Navy experience during World War II, job searches, and tributes. Materials are organized alphabetically.
  - Correspondence
    - Family, 1958-1981, undated (Box 1)
    - Maurine La Barre, 1938-1970 (Box 1)
  - Drawings (Box 1)
  - Education
    - Paper, "Kalevala, National Epic of Finland," 1932 (Box 1)
    - Papers from Princeton, 1930-1932 (Box 1)
    - Papers from Yale, 1933-1937 (Box 1)
    - Senior Thesis, Princeton, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Family Clippings and Documents (Box 1)
  - Freedom of Information files, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Job Correspondence
    - 1935-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1957 (Box 1)
  - Navy Papers, 1943-1955 (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Passport, circa 1930-1940 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Exhibits (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Identified (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Unidentified (Box 1)
    - Weston La Barre Baby Book (Box 1)
  - Tributes
    - 1969-1986, undated (Box 1)
    - Festschrift
      - Notes and Correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box 1)
      - 1986 (Box 1)
      - 1988 (Box 1)
  - Vita and Bibliography, List of Friends and Acquaintances (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1930-1996
  The Correspondence series contains mainly professional correspondence during and after La Barre's career at Duke. Because La Barre developed close friendships with fellow researchers and other professionals, much of the material contains personal as well as professional information. The materials are organized primarily by date in chronological order, but La Barre also collected the correspondence of certain correspondents separately, and this correspondence follows the yearly correspondence. It is arranged alphabetically by last name. Among these correspondents are George Devereux; Allen Ginsberg, the beat poet; Alexander Morin; Richard Evans Schultes; and Howard Stein.
  At some point, La Barre re-read his correspondence and annotated the folders and, in some cases, individual letters with his summaries and comments on their contents. It is unclear exactly when these annotations were made. Because the folder annotations contained much information but were physically deteriorating, photocopies of LaBarre's folder comments have been made and inserted in the front of the corresponding folders.
  Please note: there are two folders of personal correspondence in the Personal series. These letters are to and from family members, and were filed separately from the bulk of La Barre's correspondence.
  - 1930-1945 (Box 2)
  - January 1947-June 1947 (Box 2)
  - July 1947-December 1947 (Box 2)
  - January 1948-June 1948 (Box 2)
  - July 1948-December 1948 (Box 2)
  - January 1949-June 1949 (Box 2)
  - July 1949-December 1949 (Box 2)
  - January 1950-June 1950 (Box 2)
  - July 1950-December 1950 (Box 2)
  - January 1951-June 1951 (Box 2)
  - July 1951-December 1951 (Box 2)
  - January 1952-June 1952 (Box 2)
  - July 1952-December 1952 (Box 2)
  - January 1953-June 1953 (Box 2)
  - July 1953-December 1953 (Box 2)
  - January 1954-June 1954 (Box 2)
  - July 1954-December 1954 (Box 2)
  - January 1955-June 1955 (Box 2)
  - July 1955-December 1955 (Box 2)
  - January 1956-June 1956 (Box 2)
  - July 1956-December 1956 (Box 2)
  - January 1957-June 1957 (Box 2)
  - July 1957-December 1957 (Box 2)
  - January 1958-June 1958 (Box 2)
  - July 1958-December 1958 (Box 3)
  - January 1959-June 1959 (Box 3)
  - July 1959-December 1959 (Box 3)
  - January 1960-June 1960 (Box 3)
  - July 1960-December 1960 (Box 3)
  - January 1961-June 1961 (Box 3)
  - July 1961-December 1961 (Box 3)
  - January 1962-June 1962 (Box 3)
  - July 1962-December 1962 (Box 3)
  - January 1963-June 1963 (Box 3)
  - July 1963-December 1963 (Box 3)
  - January 1964-June 1964 (Box 3)
  - July 1964-December 1964 (Box 3)
  - January 1965-June 1965 (Box 3)
  - July 1965-December 1965 (Box 3)
  - January 1966-June 1966 (Box 3)
  - July 1966-December 1966 (Box 3)
  - January 1967-June 1967 (Box 3)
  - July 1967-December 1967 (Box 3)
  - January 1968-June 1968 (Box 3)
  - July 1968-December 1968 (Box 4)
  - January 1969-June 1969 (Box 4)
  - July 1969-December 1969 (Box 4)
  - January 1970-June 1970 (Box 4)
  - July 1970-September 1970 (Box 4)
  - October 1970-December 1970 (Box 4)
  - January 1971-June 1971 (Box 4)
  - July 1971-September 1971 (Box 4)
  - October 1971-December 1971 (Box 4)
  - January 1972-June 1972 (Box 4)
  - July 1972-October 1972 (Box 4)
  - November 1972-December 1972 (Box 4)
  - January 1973-April 1973 (Box 4)
  - May 1973-August 1973 (Box 4)
  - September 1973-December 1973 (Box 4)
  - January 1974-June 1974 (Box 4)
  - July 1974-December 1974 (Box 4)
  - January 1975-June 1975 (Box 4)
  - July 1975-September 1975 (Box 4)
  - October 1975-December 1975 (Box 4)
  - January 1976-June 1976 (Box 5)
  - July 1976-September 1976 (Box 5)
  - October 1976-December 1976 (Box 5)
  - January 1977-March 1977 (Box 5)
  - April 1977-August 1977 (Box 5)
  - September 1977-December 1977 (Box 5)
  - January 1978-June 1978 (Box 5)
  - July 1978-December 1978 (Box 5)
  - January 1979-June 1979 (Box 5)
  - July 1979-December 1979 (Box 5)
  - January 1980-June 1980 (Box 5)
  - July 1980-December 1980 (Box 5)
  - January 1981-June 1981 (Box 5)
  - July 1981-December 1981 (Box 5)
  - 1982 (Box 5)
  - 1983 (Box 5)
  - January 1984-June 1984 (Box 5)
  - July 1984-December 1984 (Box 6)
  - 1985 (Box 6)
  - 1986 (Box 6)
  - 1987 (Box 6)
  - 1988 (Box 6)
  - 1989 (Box 6)
  - 1990 (Box 6)
  - 1991 (Box 6)
  - 1992 (Box 6)
  - 1993 (Box 6)
  - 1994 (Box 6)
  - 1995 (Box 6)
  - 1996 (Box 6)
  - Undated (Box 6)
  - Banks, E. Pendleton, 1952-1971 (Box 6)
  - Beidelman, T. O., 1964-1965 (Box 6)
  - Bernheim, Molly, 1972-1980 (Box 6)
  - Bowers, Nancy, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - Buettner-Janusch, John, 1965-1972 (Box 6)
  - Cheek, Frances, 1947-1979 (Box 6)
  - Crocker, Chris, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
  - Devereux, George
    - 1945-1960 (Box 6)
    - 1961-1973 (Box 6)
    - 1974-1985, undated (Box 6)
  - Dollard, John, 1935-1940 (Box 6)
  - Gay, Peter, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1964-1977 (Box 6)
  - Grottanelli, Count Vinigi, 1965-1980 (Box 6)
  - Janeway, Elizabeth, 1970-1976 (Box 6)
  - Marsh, Robert, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Menninger, Karl 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Montagu, Ashley, 1946-1980 (Box 6)
  - Morin, Alexander
    - 1953 (Box 6)
    - 1954-1956 (Box 7)
    - post Human Animal, 1956-1959 (Box 7)
  - Schultes, Richard Evans
    - 1936-1940 (Box 7)
    - 1948-1980 (Box 7)
  - Stefansson, Vilhjalmur, 1957-1961 (Box 7)
  - Stein, Howard
    - 1975-1978 (Box 7)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Stoller, Robert, 1969-1980 (Box 7)
  - Stone, Peter, 1971-1976 (Box 7)
  - Wasson, Robert Gordon, 1950-1980 (Box 7)
- Publications, 1931-1993
  The Publications series contains many of the articles, reviews, and books that La Barre wrote during his long career. In addition to the final, published versions, La Barre often kept early drafts, correspondence with publishers, edited manuscripts, and notes. The series begins with a list of publications compiled in 1992, and follows with three folders of book reviews and other short publications. The Publications series is then divided into two main subseries: Articles and Books. La Barre published frequently throughout his career. His articles were published in scholarly publications as well as the popular press. La Barre frequently kept notes, drafts, editorial comments, correspondence, and these have been retained. Articles are arranged in chronological order. The second subseries, Books, is arranged in alphabetical order because many of La Barre's books were revised and reprinted over a period of years. The Books subseries contains published editions in addition to drafts, edited manuscripts, and correspondence. In most of the published editions, La Barre meticulously recorded positive reviews and compliments about the books given to him by colleagues.
  At some point, La Barre re-read his papers and annotated some folders and, in some cases, individual items with his summaries and comments on their contents. It is unclear exactly when these annotations were made. Because the folder annotations contained much information but were physically deteriorating, photocopies of LaBarre's folder comments have been made and inserted in the front of the corresponding folders.
  - List of Publications, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Book Reviews, Letters to the Editor, Short Communications, 1938-1969 (Box 7)
  - Book Reviews, Letters to the Editor, Short Communications, 1970-1980 (Box 7)
  - Book Reviews, 1981-1988 (Box 7)
  - Articles
    Articles are arranged in chronological order.
    - In Defense of Alexander Hall: Architecture and Women, January 1931 (Box 7)
    - Native American Beers, 1938 (Box 7)
    - Appeal of Peyote, 1939 (Box 7)
    - Psychopathology of Drinking Songs, 1939 (Box 7)
    - War and Paranoia, 1939-1940 (Box 7)
    - Cultist Drug Addiction, 1941 (Box 7)
    - The Uru of Rio Desaguadero, 1941 (Box 7)
    - Folk Medicine and Folk Science, 1942 (Box 7)
    - Reply to Richard Schultes's 'The Appeal of Peyote,' January 1942 (Box 7)
    - Administrative History of Destroyers, Atlantic Fleet, 1945 (Box 7)
    - Some Observations on Character Structure in the Orient: the Japanese, 1945 (Box 7)
    - Social Cynosure and Social Structure, 1946 (Box 7)
    - Some Observations on Character Structure in the Orient: the Chinese, 1946 (Box 7)
    - The Uru-Chipaya, 1946 (Box 7)
    - The Cultural Basis of Emotions and Gestures, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Kiowa Folk Sciences, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Potato Taxonomy Among the Aymara Indians of Bolivia, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Primitive Psychology in Native American Cultures: Peyotism and Confession, 1947 (Box 7)
    - Some Observations on Character Structure in the Orient: III. India, 1947 (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - The Aymara Indians of the Lake Titicaca Plateau, Bolivia, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Cultural Factors in Social Case Work, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Columbia University Research in Contemporary Cultures, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Folklore and Psychology, 1948 (Box 8)
    - Apperception of Attitudes, 1949 (Box 8)
    - Child Care and World Peace, 1949 (Box 8)
    - Demands Made Upon the Child by Present Day Culture, 1949 (Box 8)
    - Some Observations on Character Structure in the Orient: The Indians, circa 1949 (Box 8)
    - Wanted: A Pattern for Modern Man, 1949 (Box 8)
    - Aymara Folk Tales, 1950 (Box 8)
    - Aymara Texts, circa 1950 (Box 8)
    - The Family: Its Functions and Future, 1950 (Box 8)
    - Pediatrics, Paranoia, and Peace, 1950 (Box 8)
    - Toward World Citizenship, 1950 (Box 8)
    - Appraising Today's Pressures on Family Living, 1951 (Box 8)
    - Aymara Biologicals and Other Medicines, 1951 (Box 8)
    - Family and Symbol, 1951 (Box 8)
    - The Family: Fundamentals vs. Filigree, 1951 (Box 8)
    - Pediatrics, Paranoia and Peace, 1951 (Box 8)
    - Statement on Peyote, 1951 (Box 8)
    - Cynosures (points de mire) et structures sociales, 1953 (Box 8)
    - Letter to Editor of American Journal of Sociology, 1953 (Box 8)
    - Maumau, circa 1954 (Box 8)
    - Mobilizing a Man to Do a Job, 1954 (Box 8)
    - Strange Patterns of Marriage, 1954 (Box 8)
    - Aging as the Anthropologist Sees It, 1955-1957 (Box 8)
    - Obscenity: An Anthropological Appraisal, 1955 (Box 8)
    - The Relativity of Obscenity, 1955, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Response to Letter to Editor of American Anthropologist, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Self Respect and Mental Maturity, 1955 (Box 8)
    - The Social Cell, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Professor Widjojo Goes to a Koktel Parti, 1956 (Box 8)
    - Racism and Human Biology, 1956 (Box 8)
    - Autobiography of a Kiowa Indian, 1957 (Box 8)
    - Freud and Anthropology, 1957 (Box 8)
    - Mescalism and Peyotism, 1957 (Box 8)
    - Queens, September 1957 (Box 8)
    - The Social Worker in Cultural Change, 1957 (Box 8)
    - The Influence of Freud on Anthropology, 1958 (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - L'Influence de Freud sur l'ethnographie, 1958 (Box 8)
    - The Patient and His Families, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Religions, Rorschachs and Tranquilizers, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Adolescence: Lesson in History, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Architecture, Anthropology, and Style, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Arguments from Anthropology, 1959 (Box 8)
    - How Adolescent Are Parents? 1959 (Box 8)
    - Materia Medica of the Aymara, 1959 (Box 8)
    - Religion, Rorschachs, and Tranquilizers, 1959-1960 (Box 8)
    - Chapel Hill Psychiatry Textbook, 1960 (Box 8)
    - Haring Festschrift, 1960 (Box 8)
    - Neurotic Defense Mechanisms in Supernatural Religion, 1960 (Box 8)
    - Relation Between Parents and Children, 1960 (Box 8)
    - Twenty Years of Peyote Studies, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Universal Biological Features of the Family, 1960 (Box 9)
    - What Linguists Tell Anthropologists, 1960 (Box 9)
    - Art and Mythology: the Present State of the Problem, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Biosocial Unity of the Family, 1961 (Box 9)
    - People are Different, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Psychoanalysis in Anthropology, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Spier Festschrift, 1961 (Box 9)
    - The Well-Disciplined Parent, 1961 (Box 9)
    - Architecture, Anthropology, and City Planning, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Les relations entre les parents et les enfants, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Paralanguage, Kinesics, and Cultural Anthropology, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Some Observations on Character in the Orient: The Japanese, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Transference Cures in Religious Cults and Social Groups, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica articles 1963 (Box 9)
    - Comments on Hockett and Ascher, 1964 (Box 9)
    - Confession as Cathartic Therapy in American Indian Tribes, 1964 (Box 9)
    - The Diabolic Root, 1964 (Box 9)
    - The Language of Emotion and Gesture, 1964 (Box 9)
    - The Narcotic Complex of the New World, 1964 (Box 9)
    - OAR/SORO Report, 1964 (Box 9)
    - Paralinguistics, Kinesics, and Cultural Anthropology, 1964 (Box 9)
    - The Snake Handling Cult of the American Southeast, 1964 (Box 9)
    - UNESCO Dictionary articles, 1964 (Box 9)
    - Aymara Folklore and Folk Temperament, 1965 (Box 9)
    - 'The Worm in the Honeysuckle': A Case Study of a Child's Hysterical Blindness, 1965 (Box 9)
    - The Aymara: History and Worldview, 1966 (Box 9)
    - Die Kulturelle Grundlage von Emotionen und Gesten, 1966 (Box 9)
    - The Dream, the Charisma, and the Culture-Hero, 1966 (Box 9)
    - Geza Roheim, 1966 (Box 9)
    - The Lessons of Anthropology for Urban Design, 1966 (Box 9)
    - Some Comments Concerning Hockett and Ascher's The Human Revolution, 1966 (Box 9)
    - Le reve, le charisme et le herosculturel, 1967 (Box 9)
    - Preface to Devereux's From Anxiety to Method in the Behavioral Sciences, 1967 (Box 9)
    - The Trouble with Young People Nowadays Is.. ., 1967 (Box 9)
    - Article on Ethnopsychology, 1968-1971 (Box 9)
    - Comments on Hall's Proxemics, 1968 (Box 9)
    - Normal Adolescence: Its Dynamics and Impact, 1968 (Box 9)
    - Personality from a Psychoanalytic Viewpoint, 1968 (Box 9)
    - Adolescence, the Crucible of Change, 1969 (Box 9)
    - Movements religieux d'acculturation en Amerique du Nord, 1969 (Box 9)
    - The Triple Crisis: Adolescence, Early Marriage, and Parenthood, 1969 (Box 9)
    - Drug Anthology, circa 1970-1971 (Box 9)